Guide to the Rust Engineering Company Records, 1905-1989 AIS.2006.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Rust Engineering Company Records
1905-1989
1908-1967
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Rust Engineering Company
AIS.2006.06
39.03 Linear Feet (87 boxes, 5 rolls of microfilm, 1 oversize folder)
The Rust Engineering Company specialized in the design and construction of equipment and facilities for heavy industry, including furnaces, boiler settings, industrial chimneys, and entire manufacturing and processing plants. This collection documents the management of Rust Engineering's Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, headquarters by its first two presidents, Stirling Murray Rust and Stirling Murray Rust, Jr., through correspondence, job and financial reports, meeting minutes, promotional items, newspaper clippings, and photographs. Digital reproductions of the collection are available online.
History
The Rust Engineering Company was founded in 1905 as a partnership between three brothers from Virginia; Ellsworth Marshall Rust (E.M. Rust), Edmund Jennings Lee Rust (Lee Rust), and Stirling Murray Rust (S.M. Rust). Originally created to handle boiler sales and brickwork for the Rust Boiler Company, which was owned by three older Rust brothers, Rust Engineering quickly expanded into other subsets of design and construction and was soon building foundations, power houses, and eventually entire manufacturing plants. Rust Engineering was also a leading builder of industrial chimneys and furnaces, which were in high demand throughout most of the twentieth century.
In 1913, Rust Engineering opened an office in Pittsburgh, where the Rust Boiler Company was already established. The small office was headed by S.M. Rust, who already had experience working in the Pittsburgh region. In 1920 the partnership was dissolved and Rust Engineering was incorporated into three separate companies based in Pittsburgh, Birmingham, and Washington, D.C. S.M. Rust became president of the Pittsburgh companies, while vice-presidents E.M. Rust and Lee Rust headed the Washington, D.C., and Birmingham companies, respectively. The partnership struggled at first, facing railroad delays, uncooperative workers, and droughts in the south. In the mid-1920s, the Washington, D.C. company was dissolved and became a sales office, and the Birmingham and Pittsburgh companies merged. The official headquarters was in Pittsburgh, but the Birmingham office continued to operate independently for many years. The company survived these initial difficulties, as well as the Depression that followed, through its versatility. By taking on everything from simple repair jobs to complex design projects, the company could adapt to major changes.
In 1939, S.M. Rust, Jr. became the operating manager for the Pittsburgh office, although his father remained president until 1944. A mechanical engineer, S.M. Rust, Jr. had the daunting task of managing a constant supply of government contracts during World War II. Rust Engineering's experience with many types of industrial construction made it ideal for wartime work.
By the 1950s, Rust Engineering was a leading engineering firm known for its furnaces, paper mills, concrete work, and "turn-key" plants, so called because the company handled everything from the blueprints to the installation of machinery, leaving the plant fully operational and the keys in the hands of management. Rust Engineering took contracts across the United States, but was especially important in Pittsburgh, where it built for Westinghouse, Pittsburgh Plate and Glass, and many of the city's steel mills. Rust Engineering also built the foundations and steel framework of the Koppers Building, one of the distinctive features of the Pittsburgh skyline.
In 1967, Rust Engineering was sold to Litton Industries. In the years following the sale, the company was merged and reassigned numerous times, and in 1971 its headquarters was moved from Pittsburgh to Birmingham, Alabama. As of 2020, Rust has been included in several acquisitions and in 2014 Rust Constructors was acquired by AECOM and its headquarters are in Houston, Texas. Historical detail about Rust Engineering's work at times is described at the series level.
Scope and Content Notes
The majority of the documents in this collection follow the Rust Engineering Company from its founding in 1905 until its sale to Litton Industries in 1967 -- the time when Rust was a family-run organization. Although it contains a variety of material, the strength of the collection lies in the correspondence and project files of the company's first two presidents, S.M. Rust and S.M. Rust, Jr., who operated from the Pittsburgh office.
Working at a time when most long-distance business communication was by letter or telegram, both presidents wrote constantly to their officers, their brothers and uncles at branch offices, foremen and site superintendents, lawyers, financial advisors, other companies, and clients. Their discussions, which are often detailed and sometimes personal, show how they handled management decisions day to day; a typical letter might inquire about a shipment of brick, settle a dispute between workers, or discuss contacts in the paper mill industry. A great deal of correspondence is devoted to individual jobs, since the presidents were ultimately responsible for arranging contracts and correcting any problems that arose, such as delays, union strikes, or unexpected costs. The frequency and detail of the letters makes it possible to see what was important in the office at nearly any time from 1918 to 1949.
Taken as a whole, the president's files demonstrate how the company reacted and adapted to the major events of the twentieth century, as well as changing ideals in business culture. Rust Engineering profited from the need for steel and steam power during the 1920s, survived the Great Depression, served the home front during World War II, and reverted to peacetime operations afterwards. In the process, Rust Engineering also transformed from a small, family-run company offering a single specific service into a large corporation overseeing multiple projects of many types across the United States and around the world.
In addition to providing a record of one company's changes over time, the collection can also be seen as the history of the careers of S.M. Rust and his son S.M. Rust, Jr. The files span S.M. Rust's career from his time as a 27-year-old worker in New Orleans, just beginning his professional work, through his retirement from the presidency in 1944. His letters are clear and logical and often explain in detail the reasoning behind the decisions he made. He was especially attentive to human resource decisions, since he believed that getting the "right man for the job" was key to the success of any business. There is little evidence of self-censorship in these files; S.M. Rust discussed the strengths and weaknesses of employees with honesty and fairness, and he did not hesitate to tell them what they did wrong. More telling, though, is that his workers often had no qualms about responding to their employer in an equally frank tone. He maintained a strong sense of loyalty to those who worked for him, and attempted to solve or prevent problems rather than simply replace a worker.
Similarly, the files trace S.M. Rust, Jr.'s transition from a management position to president of the company. Like his father, he had to make personnel decisions and was concerned with character and potential. Perhaps the most striking example is a series of letters in which S.M. Rust, Jr. is the only employer among ten companies willing to consider a former Alcatraz prisoner for a job. S.M. Rust, Jr. was also involved in the local community as a member of several social and charitable organizations.
The record of president's files ends abruptly after 1949. The few materials from after the company's sale to Litton Industries in 1967 are mostly published items, probably collected by the Rust family.
In addition to the president's files, the collection contains minute books and charters, promotional items, an extensive clipping collection, and approximately 400 photographs of construction sites and employees at work. A photo album from 1917 and 1918 captures the construction of structures for the steel industry in Alabama, including coal tipples, coke ovens, storage bins, screening plants, and blast furnaces.
Timeline
1905: The Rust Engineering Company is founded in Birmingham, Alabama, as a partnership between three brothers.
1913: Pittsburgh Office opens.
1920: Partnership is dissolved, and the company is incorporated into three financially independent companies: Rust Engineering of Delaware (Pittsburgh Office), Rust Engineering of Maryland (D.C. Office), and Rust Engineering of Alabama (Birmingham Office).
1918: Rust purchases the Birmingham Clay Products Company to manufacture brick.
1925: Eric Plagwit is hired and placed at the head of a new Chimney Department.
Mid-1920s: Rust Engineering of Maryland is dissolved, assets go to Pittsburgh.
1927: Rust's first subsidiary, the Rust Furnace Company, is formed.
1936: The Allegheny Industrial Electrical Company is formed as a subsidiary.
1938: The Woodbridge Clay Product Company becomes an affiliate.
1939: S.M. Rust, Jr. becomes operating manager of the Pittsburgh Company.
1944: S.M. Rust retires from the presidency and becomes Chairman of the Board of Directors; S.M. Rust, Jr. becomes president.
1967: Rust is bought by Litton Industries, becoming a division of that company.
1971: Rust's headquarters is moved from Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, to Birmingham, Alabama.
1972: Rust is bought by Wheelabrator-Frye
1981: Wheelabrator-Frye acquires Pullman, Inc. Rust's northeast operations are merged with Swindell operations, forming Swindell Rust.
1981: The Rust Engineering Company becomes a division of Kellogg Rust, Inc., still owned by Wheelabrator-Frye.
1982: Kellogg Rust forms Rust International Corporation by merging all of Rust's former divisions.
1983: Wheelabrator-Frye merges with the Signal Companies, Inc. Rust becomes one of the signal companies.
1985: The Signal Companies and Allied Corporation merge into Allied-Signal, Inc.
1986: Kellogg Rust is dissolved. Rust International becomes part of Wheelabrator Technologies, Inc., a subsidiary of the Henley Group, Inc. The Henley Group had been created in a spin-off of Allied-Signal to its shareholders.
1990: Waste Management Inc. becomes Rust's parent company by increasing its equity ownership of Wheelabrator Technologies.
1992: Rust International, Inc. is formed by combining parts of Waste Management companies Chemical Waste Management, Wheelabrator Technologies, and the Brand Companies.
1993: Waste Management changes its name to WMX Technologies, Inc.
1995: Rust is owned 60 percent by WMX Technologies and 40 percent by Wheelabrator Technologies.
1996: Raytheon Engineers & Constructors, part of Raytheon Company, acquires Rust.
2000: Morrison Knudsen Corporation acquires Raytheon Engineers & Constructors and creates Washington Group International, Inc. It is one of the largest engineering and construction firms in the United States. Rust is now known as Rust Constructors, Inc.
2007: Washington Group and its subsidiaries acquired by URS Corporation.
2014: URS acquired by AECOM. Rust Constructors headquarters moved to Houston, TX
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into the following series and subseries. The president's files have been described by decade in order to highlight the changes. The presidents' office files were kept in three basic ways; correspondence between the presidents and others, files on individual jobs, and subject files containing information on particular events or problems. While they form subseries, it is important to note that they may not contain all information about a particular topic; in most cases, more information can be found in the correspondence files. Also note that while the filing system in the president's correspondence sometimes appears continuous and may contain documents from every working day, it is not a complete record. The office's main criteria for retaining documents changed over time. Please see the series and subseries notes for more detail.
Series I. Histories and General Information
Series II. Minute Books, 1920-1967
Series III. President's Office Files, 1905-1919
Series IV. President's Office Files, 1920-1929
Series V. President's Office Files, 1930-1939
Series VI. President's Office Files, 1940-1941
Series VII. Affiliate Companies, 1927-1974
Series VIII. Publicity, 1920-1989
Series IX. Photographs, 1911-1967
Series X. New Materials Added, 1915-1989
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Stirling Murray Rust, Jr. on February 2, 2006. Additions made on December 14, 2018.
Previous Citation
Rust Engineering Company Records, 1905-1989, AIS.2006.06, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the collection are available electronically at http://historicpittsburgh.org/collection/rust-engineering-company-records.
Separated Material
Photographs and microfilm are housed in the Media Room. Boxes 43 and 65 are oversized and housed separately.
Photograph albums; Office files; Minute books; Microfilms; Correspondence; Executives; Brochures; Black-and-white negatives; Black-and-white photographs; Sales personnel; Engineers; Draftsmen (People in engineering); Construction workers; Chief financial officers; Bricklayers; Labor unions; Industrial management; Industrial engineering; Industrial buildings -- Foundations; Business and Industry; Gunite; Furnaces; Engineering; Construction industry -- Management; Coke plants; Chimneys; Brickmaking; Mechanical engineers; Boilers; Mechanical engineering; Paper mills; Pulp mills; Construction equipment operators; Steam-boilers; Steel industry and trade; Strikes and lockouts; Birmingham (Ala.); Holt (Ala.); Depressions -- 1929; New York (N.Y.); Pittsburgh (Pa.); Washington (D.C.); Industrial engineers; Clippings (Information artifacts); Rust, Edmund Jennings Lee; Rust, Ellsworth Marshall; Rust, Stirling Murray, Jr.; Rust, Stirling Murray; Allegheny Industrial Electrical Company; Rust Engineering Company; Rust Furnace Company; Vibroflotation Foundation Company; United States. National Recovery Administration
- Histories and General Information, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains material created or collected by Rust Engineering to document its own history. Some of the information was gathered for short articles about the company, which were written for special events or publications. The authors contacted members of the Rust family and other long-term employees for information on the company's first years, as well as their personal memories and anecdotes. Their responses are present alongside research notes and drafts of the history articles. Drafts of book entitled, Engineering for Excellence, Building for Permanence: The Rust Engineering Company, 1905-1975, written by Norma Shields, provide a solid summary of the company's major changes and accomplishments. The company also kept newsletters and a small amount of ephemeral material in its history files, which have been included in a separate subseries.
  - History Articles and Research Notes, 1.
    Files related to history articles contain a variety of documents, including drafts, correspondence, notes, and questionnaires.
    - Article about the Rust Boiler Company, 1904-1907 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - List of company officers, 1920-1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Booklet on Rust history and qualifications, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - History of Rust Engineering as told by R.L. Hess, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Article, The Rust Engineering Company: A History written by J. Paul Scheetz for The Bicentennial History of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Personal histories collected for History of the Rust Engineering Company by Arthur M. Lawrence, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Changes in company structure after merge with Litton Industries, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Rust's History and Experience, written for Litton Industries, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Drafts and correspondence for Engineering for Excellence, Building for Permanence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 01-03)
    - Histories of Rust departments and subsidiaries, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Rust of Virginia: Genealogical and Biographical Sketches of the Descendents of William Rust, 1654-1940 by Ellsworth Marshall Rust (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - General Information, 2.
    Rust Engineering retained examples of directories and other items published for internal use for inclusion in an archive. They provide information about the company's benefits, insurance policies, and other employee concerns. Rust Engineering's newsletter, The Rust Triangle, was published from 1957 to 1967 and contains articles on particular jobs, events, individual employees, and areas of the company otherwise unrepresented by the collection, such as the Women's Auxiliary.
    - General information and policies for employees, 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 01-02)
    - Phone books, 1958-1969 (Box 3, Folder 03-04)
    - Birmingham Office Personnel Directory, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Pittsburgh Office Personnel Directory, c1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Birmingham Office Personnel Directory, c1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Field Office Personnel Directory, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Rust Civic Service Award and Fifty Year Medallions, 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Scrapbook of internal announcements and leaflets, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - The Rust Triangle, Vol. I-XI, 1957-1967 (Box 5, Volume 01-02)
    - Reactions to The Rust Triangle, 1957-1966 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Minute Books, 1920-1967; II.
  Series II is comprised of bound volumes and microfilmed copies of minute books for the Rust Engineering Company of Delaware (the Pittsburgh office) and ten of Rust's subsidiaries and affiliates. They cover the time from the founding of each company or affiliate until its dissolution or until 1967, when Rust was purchased by Litton Industries.
  Each set of books begins with records documenting the creation of the company, its bylaws, the minutes of its first meeting, and in some cases stock ledgers and other financial documents. After this initial information, minutes almost always represent one of three types of meetings; the Annual Meeting of Stockholders was held once a year to choose the Board of Directors for the following year. Immediately after this, at the Meeting of the Board of Directors, the board would appoint a president, vice president, secretary, and treasurer. Special Meetings of the Board of Directors could be held at any time throughout the year to decide courses of action on major issues -- especially financial ones -- such as opening accounts or selling stock. Minutes for these meetings are brief, usually consisting of little more than a tally of votes and formal declarations of any decisions made that day, but they do provide a complete record of board members and officers until 1967, as well as documentation of the companies' involvement with particular regions, industries, and projects. There are also a few additional document types, including a list of the government contract projects which Rust completed during the 1940s to serve the war effort.
  Minutes were originally bound into books, but in some cases only microfilmed copies remain. It is likely that the originals were passed to Litton Industries when the company was sold. A paper index to the microfilmed books can be found in box 8.
  - Potomac Clay Products Company, 1929-1930 (Box 5, Volume 3)
  - Bolivar Clay Products Company Minute Book, Vol. 1-2, 1921-1959 (Box 6, Volume 01-02)
  - Rust Construction Company, 1927-1934 (Box 7, Volume 1)
  - Rust Gunite Company, 1930 (Box 7, Volume 2)
  - Loudoun-Rust Company Minute Book, 1930-1934 (Box 7, Volume 3)
  - Rust Engineering minute books, 1920-1943 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 8, Reel 1)
  - Rust Engineering minute books, 1945-1956 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 8, Reel 2)
  - Rust Engineering minute books, 1957-1960 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 8, Reel 3.1)
  - Vibroflotation Foundation Co. minute books, 1953-c1966 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 8, Reel 3.2)
  - Vibroflotaion Foundation Co. minute book, 1966-1997 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 8, Reel 4.1)
  - Allegheny Industrial Electrical Co. minute books, 1936-1967 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 8, Reel 4.2)
  - Rust Furnace Co. minute books, 1929-1947 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 8, Reel 4.3)
  - Rust Furnace Co. minute book, 1957-1967 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 8, Reel 5.1)
  - Doyle and Russell, Inc. minute book, 1962-1967 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 8, Reel 5.2)
  - Rust Engineering Co. (Canada) Ltd. minute book, 1936-1967 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 8, Reel 5.3)
- President's Office Files, 1905-1919; III.
  Rust Engineering was founded in 1905, but little survives from its first few years in Alabama, when the company installed boilers for the Rust Boiler Company. The earliest letters, written from 1907 to 1910, are between officers at both Rust Engineering and the Rust Boiler Company in Alabama and S.M. Rust, who had been sent to New Orleans in an attempt to break into the boiler market. Letters from the sales department instruct him on marketing the company to this part of the south.
  Despite his southern roots, S.M. Rust was no stranger to Pittsburgh when the Rust Engineering office opened there in 1913. He had moved to the city at the age of seventeen to work in the steel mills, where he was a laborer, blueprint boy, and eventually a member of design and engineering departments. The new office employed a small team of engineers, but jobs were non-existent at first. One employee, looking back, credited S.M. Rust holding the company together with only "good humor, his companionship and his fellowship with his employees," because the company could not afford to pay them.
  Files from these first years in Pittsburgh are sparse compared to later years, but most discuss the brickwork and boiler jobs that the company was able to acquire.
  - Correspondence, 1.
    Items in this subseries are not in original order, but have been filed chronologically by month. When exchanges covering several months were found together, they were filed by the date of the earliest letter
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, 1907 (Box 9, Folder 01-02)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-November, 1908 (Box 9, Folder 03-06)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, 1910-1915 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, 1915 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-July, 1916 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, August, 1916 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-August, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 03-04)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, September-December, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, January-September, 1919 (Box 10, Folder 06-08)
    - S.M. Rust correspondence, October-December, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Subject Files, 2.
    The subject files from this period are mainly financial reports tracking the company's progress. The Boiler Brickwork Quantity Sheets give specifics for the amount of brick needed to complete a given job.
    - "Early years", 1905-1919 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Financial agreements, 1914 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Financial statements, 1916 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Business report, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Boiler Brickwork Quantity Sheets, February 12, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 06-07)
    - Business reports, April and July, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Financial information, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- President's Office Files, 1920-1929; IV.